Back in the 10th year of Yuankang
元康十年那会儿
Our Xuan Kingdom's annual tax revenue
我大宣国一年的税收
Could reach over 18 million taels
能达到一千八百余万两
Why, when it reached Chancellor Xie
缘何到谢相手里
Only 10.5 million taels remained?
只剩下了一千零五十万两
I
臣
Deserve death ten thousand times
臣万死
Your Majesty
陛下
After several major battles in recent years
前几年几场大仗打下来
Border trade with the Wuzhao was closed
边境与邬伖的互市就关了
This
这
Lost a large amount of revenue
这少了一大笔收入
Your Majesty
陛下您
Implemented benevolent policies for the people
对百姓施仁政
Taxes everywhere were reduced, this
各地赋税均有所减免 这
Lost another large amount of revenue
这又少了一大笔收入
Your Majesty
陛下
For Your Majesty's grand ambitions
为陛下的宏图大志
I will definitely find a way
臣一定琢磨出办法
To quickly fill the treasury
尽快令国库充盈
Physicians often say
医者常言
Severe illness requires strong medicine
重病当以猛药
If there is any blame
旦有骂名由臣
I will bear it
来担
Alright, alright
好了好了
I'm tired
朕乏了
Think it over yourself
自己琢磨吧
All withdraw
都退下吧
Yes
是
I take my leave
臣告退
Come out
出来吧
Your Majesty
陛下
I have verified everything
事情臣都已经查实了
The Xie family colluded with factions
谢家勾结朋党
Layered exploitation of state taxes
对国家税赋层层盘剥
Originally two hundred taels of silver
原本二百两银子
When it reached the court
到了朝廷手里
Only one hundred taels remained
就只剩下一百两
Also
还有
This year's Ministry of Revenue's list of official appointments
今年户部陈奏的官员任选名单
More than half are Chen clan members
里头一大半都是陈氏族人
The remaining half
剩下一半
Most are also from the Xie and Zu families
多数也是谢家 祖家
And their retainers and students
还有他们的门客学生
As for
至于
The mad horse at the hunting ground
之前在猎场
That nearly collided with Your Majesty
险些冲撞陛下的那匹疯马
I
臣
Also heard some rumors
也听闻一点小道消息
Saying
说
According to informants
据线人所说
Because the Wuzhao are skilled with horses
因为邬伖人善马
So in General Zu Yue's army
所以祖月祖将军军中
They once developed a kind of
曾经研制过一种
Fierce drug that can make warhorses go mad
可以让战马发狂的烈药
Your Majesty
陛下
Be careful
小心啊
And that mad horse that nearly collided with Your Majesty
而那天险冲撞陛下的疯马
Was exactly given this drug
正是用了这种药
The informant also said
线人还说
That drugged horse
那匹被下了药的马
Why are you beating around the bush?
你绕什么弯子
I told you to speak, so speak
我让你说就说
That horse
那匹马
Was originally meant for the second prince
原本是要留给二殿下的
Only
只不过
The crown prince happened to ride it
恰巧太子给骑走了
Enough
行了
Keep this matter buried in your stomach
这件事情烂在你肚子里
Understand?
明白吗
I understand
微臣明白
Dismissed
下去吧
Chancellor Xie Jian'an
谢建安这个丞相
Really got his money's worth
当得可真是值啊
Now
现在
We are not yet firmly established
咱们立足未稳
It's not yet time to move against them
还不是动他们的时候
I have a word of warning for you
朕有句话提醒你
Don't trust and rely too much on your subordinates
不要太信任和依靠门下
Don't become their puppet
不要变成他们的傀儡
You and your elder brother are family
你和你大哥才是一家人
Father really had it difficult back then
父皇当年真不容易啊
You lamented the great families growing powerful
你感叹世家做大
Restraining you everywhere
对你处处掣肘
But now
可如今
The state still has many matters
国家还有许多事情
That require these people to handle
都需要这些人来做
Yet you cannot move against them
你偏偏又动不得他们
Now the Chen and Xie families
眼下陈谢两家
Frequently intermarry
频繁联姻
If they unite
他们联合起来
Will only become harder to deal with
只会越来越难对付
Reform is necessary
必须要改制了
But reform
可改制
How should it be done?
要如何改呢
Treatise on Land
土地十论
Sheng'er's political ideas are very good
盛儿政论的想法很好
Can indeed solve Xuan's current
的确能解决宣国当下的
Contradictions and problems
矛盾和问题
But some ideas are still too one-sided
但是有些想法还是太片面
To successfully implement it
要想成功推行
We need someone with a high enough position
还需要一个位置足够高
And
而且
Who can put the state's interests first
能够把国家利益放在首位
And is absolutely trustworthy
又绝对能够信任的人
Marquis of Yongning
永宁侯
Xie Xuan
谢玄